<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to a gentleman in the country concerning the price of guineas</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04005</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617819</idno>
  <idno type="VID">175278</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240909095</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R179575</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">51617819</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04005)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175278)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2726:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to a gentleman in the country concerning the price of guineas</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>3 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Feb. 29, 95/6.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Columbia University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Guinea (Coin) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Coinage --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Currency question --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Pas </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter_fragment">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:175278:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>should be small, yet the frequent Returns from Neighbour Countries, will give sufficient Encouragement to such Undertakers. So that it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the overvaluing one Species must destroy the other, which being thereby undervalued is advantageously Exported. And whosoever will take the Pains to consult the <hi>Custom-House</hi> Books, may judge what Mischief this Kingdom has sustained by the late prodigious Importation of Gold and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of Silver; which could not be done upon fair Trade, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over has been a means to keep the Exchange low; whereby all foreign Commodities and Naval Stores were rendred more dear, and all Remisses for the Army abroad more chargeable by almost a third part.</p>
            <p>But this is not the only way whereby the Plague of Guineas Ravages the Kingdom; for it absolutely Confounds Trade: because wherever two sorts of Measures of things valuable are used, the one true the other false, all Payments must be dubious and uncertain; so that the Species of Gold and Silver are rendred useless and unserviceable to each other, being not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Communication. For how can Truth subsist with Falshood, or what Agreement can there be between the real intrinsick Value of the Silver, and the false denominative Price of Gold, which the former will avoid as an Infection? It being a fundamental Principle of Commerce and Contracts, that as the General opinion and consent of the common Market of the World, has appointed Gold and Silver to be the proportional Measure and Pledge of Equivalence in all Bargains whatsoever for other things; so the same General consent has appointed between Gold and Silver a proportion of Value to each other, founded on the universal Reason of Plenty and Scarcity: which Opinion and Consent, is not to be imposed upon by the fraudulent Artifices of particular Men, nor even to be controled by the Power of absolute Princes, nor by any other Sovereign Power whatsoever; which tho it exert it self to the utmost in order to force Obedience in particular States, cannot affect other Nations; and considering the Fallibility and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of human Nature, may often become Injurious and Destructive.</p>
            <p>And while I point at violation of Contracts hereby caused, I am obliged to take notice of the good nature of the Landlords of <hi>England,</hi> who for some time past, have contentedly received their Rents in Clipt Money not worth above Fifty pounds, or in Guineas not worth above Seventy for a hundred, while the Tenants have grown Rich and very well paid their Rents, as well they might, when they enjoy'd so great a proportion of what was properly the Landlords Income. The Rents of <hi>England</hi> are so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable an Interest that they ought to command all others, being common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly computed at fifteen Millions yearly, which reckoned but at fifteen Years Purchase, amounts to Two Hundred Twenty Five Millions; an Estate so great, that no other in the Nation can compare with it.</p>
            <p>But the greatest Landlord is the King, whose Revenues and Taxes are insufficiently paid by the over-value of Guineas, if Received into the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer;</hi> and all Loans to him rendred also insufficient, to the great Disappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Damage of the Government. Moreover the Revenues of the Church are lessened, all publick Settlements of Charity defrauded, all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuities
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175278:1"/>and Pensions, all Lenders on Bonds, Mortgages, and all Creditors whose Debts have been of long continuance; in short all Persons who have just Pretension to the real Value, who are no less abused by Money of false Denomination, than by Money Clipt or of base Alloy.</p>
            <p>Now I hear a great outcry, that by the reduction of Guineas to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Price many Persons will be losers. But who are they? the Landlords and all others who had a true Title to the Guinea, tho it were intrinsecally worth what it now passes for: but the Tenants and Traders have no such Title, for they raised their Goods in proportion to the rise of Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, otherwise they were blind; and the Foreigner all this while has bought the Product of the Nation so much below its Price. I confess nothing ought to be done to the Detriment of Trade, which as the Life and Soul, actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates the heavy mass of Lands; but I cannot without indignation mention the baseness of some Traders even of the greatest figure, who have made their Interest the standard of their Reason, and by Publishing false Notions have laboured to deceive those unacquainted with the Mystery of Trade.</p>
            <p>I think fit also to inform you of some new pretences of raising the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of the Silver, so as to pass for more than it now doth, that so it may come up to the Guinea: this plainly is a double Cheat, and will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly increase the Mischiefs I have before related.</p>
            <p>Now because the small quantity of Silver to be Coin'd, being little more than a Million intrinsick, cannot possibly be sufficient to answer the Trade of the Kingdom, and to circulate the National Rents, the Publick Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues and Taxes; I do humbly conceive it necessary, <hi>First</hi> to establish the Price of Guineas by a Law, with a Penalty if paid for more than that Price; and that Guineas be made by Law the current Money of <hi>England,</hi> in order to answer all Contracts whatsoever. <hi>Secondly</hi> to increase the Silver Coin by calling in Plate: in order whereto I humbly Propose, that a Law be made enjoining all Persons to bring in a certain number of Ounces of Plate, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their several Conditions and Degrees; with particular respect to the greatness of their Estates Real and Personal, tho otherwise of the same Degree, as Gentleman, Esquire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the Penalty of One Shilling for every Ounce of Plate not brought in: so that this Imposition may be some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like the nature of a Pole, which may be executed with the utmost ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, since no Man has any thing taken from him but the Fashion of his Plate, which shall be Coin'd at the Publick Charge, and return'd to him in full Value according to Weight. It may be Presum'd no Man will grudge at this which is so much for the Service of his Country, since the increase of the Silver Species is so absolutely necessary to circulate the Rents and Debts of all Persons, and to answer all Payments whatsoever.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Feb.</hi> 29. 95/6</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>I am Sir Your humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:175278:2"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>